<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://limengbinggz.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://limengbinggz.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2026-01-16T05:35:45+00:00</updated><id>https://limengbinggz.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal website
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Your PhD Should Not Be Lonely</title><link href="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/find-peers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your PhD Should Not Be Lonely" /><published>2026-01-16T05:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-16T05:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/find-peers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/find-peers/"><![CDATA[<p>When people are asked to describe their PhD journey in one word, the answers are often challenging, rewarding, or exhausting. All of those are true. 
And yet, for many of us, loneliness quietly becomes the default setting, especially after coursework ends and everyone disappears into their own research bubble. 
Looking back at my own journey, one of the most important things I did do during my PhD was to build my own support group.</p>

<p>My academic sister <a href="https://profiles.ucl.ac.uk/103633-stephanie-wu">Stephanie Wu</a>, previously at Harvard Biostatistics and currently at UCL, became one of the most important people throughout my graduate school. We initially met at ENAR 2022 (one of the most important biostatistics conferences in the US), which was also the first in-person conference after COVID. 
We were assigned to the same session and were immediately struck by how similar our talks were. Later, we realized that Stephanie’s advisor was a close collaborator of mine and a member of my thesis committee.</p>

<p>The second time we met in person was at JSM 2022 (the biggest statistics conference in North America), when we were assigned to the same session again. In 2023, we bumped into each other at one more conference. Every time I saw Stephanie, I felt her energy. She was always passionate, soft-spoken, smiling, and thoughtful.</p>

<p>Towards the end of 2023, Stephanie texted me one day: <em>Do you want to set up regular calls just to talk about whatever we like?</em> Honestly I hesitated. I was extremely introverted and always wanted to avoid social interactions whenever possible. But out of politeness, I said yes, and we put up weekly Zoom calls on our calendars.</p>

<p>At the first call, I had no idea what to say. Unlike meetings with my advisor, there was no agenda to prepare. Thankfully Stephanie led the conversation about her research problems. By the second call, I found myself enjoying the conversation, as we started sharing life events in addition to research. 
Even before I realized it, I was actually looking forward to our meetings.</p>

<p>We talked about everything: food we were craving, trips we wanted to take, random gossip, frustrations with advisors, stories about our partners, and life outside academia. Research topics slipped in too. We brainstormed ideas, debugged code for each other, derived math formulas together, shared papers, and sanity-checked half-baked thoughts that we would never dare to say out loud in a group meeting. Later, as graduation approached, we mocked interviews, shared job postings, and helped each other rehearse interview.</p>

<p>In fact, around the time we started our regular calls, both of us were struggling badly. It was right after COVID. We felt isolated, depressed, and unmotivated. The excitement of starting a PhD was long gone, and the thesis felt like a distant, heavy burden. Throughout COVID, I lived with my partner together. When my partner returned to in-person work while I was still working from home, staying alone became terrible. I felt unmotivated to do anything, I lost appetite (I ate nothing but a small dinner each day), and developed the ability to cry any moment.</p>

<p>Those weekly calls with Stephanie did not magically fix everything overnight. They did not suddenly make my research easy or my anxiety disappear. But they gave my weeks a rhythm. They gave me a reason to show up as <em>myself</em>, not as a “productive PhD student”. Knowing that someone would listen, understand, help, and not judge made the rest of the week feel survivable.</p>

<p>Gradually, we both got better. Work resumed in a steady way. Papers got written. Chapters got drafted. Job applications went out. We both graduated. After finishing our PhDs, we still talk regularly, despite being in different time zones. Now we talk about life, new jobs, and all the joys and chaos that come with moving on.</p>

<p>That is why I genuinely believe our PhD should not be lonely. Large groups and formal mentoring structures are wonderful, but sometimes all it takes is one peer or two and a recurring calendar invite. 
This peer can share the same research area or work on a different one, can come from the same or a different department/school. What really matters is consistency, trust, and mutual respect.</p>

<p>What made the difference for me was putting recurring events on our calendars. The recurring calls became a psychological anchor for each week, even if we occasionally canceled or rescheduled. I just had to show up, knowing that I did not need to be perfectly prepared or in a good mood. A similar experience with another group of peer has taught me that when too many meetings are skipped, restarting becomes surprisingly hard.</p>

<p>Equally important was how we treated each other in those conversations. We showed up without judgment. We were honest and generous with what we knew - ideas, papers, job leads, and half-baked thoughts. 
Over time, I became much happier as I adopted the mindset that the more I supported my peer, the easier my own path felt. Support always comes back in unexpected ways. When both sides hold this belief, the relationship stops feeling like an obligation and becomes sustainable.</p>

<p>If you are early in your PhD, or even in the middle and feeling stuck, I hope my story encourages you to reach out. Identify your peer(s), suggest regular calls, and put them on the calendar.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="grad-school" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When people are asked to describe their PhD journey in one word, the answers are often challenging, rewarding, or exhausting. All of those are true. And yet, for many of us, loneliness quietly becomes the default setting, especially after coursework ends and everyone disappears into their own research bubble. Looking back at my own journey, one of the most important things I did do during my PhD was to build my own support group.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Following the Rules, Until I Did Not</title><link href="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/break-the-rules/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Following the Rules, Until I Did Not" /><published>2026-01-11T16:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-11T16:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/break-the-rules</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/break-the-rules/"><![CDATA[<p>I grew up as a very “乖” kid in China, a Chinese word that has no exact English equivalent but loosely means being well-behaved and obedient, and meeting the expectations that parents and teachers set for good kids and students. I followed rules carefully, behaved the way teachers expected, and internalized the idea that being a good student meant doing things the “right” way. Questioning authority rarely crossed my mind. Rules felt absolute, and obeying them felt like safety and virtue.</p>

<p>Coming to the United States for college slowly changed how I saw things. I did not become rebellious, nor did I stop valuing rules. What changed was my belief that rules were always reasonable. I began to realize that many rules existed more because of convenience, habit, or history than because they were optimal for learning or growth. Following them without reflection started to feel less like discipline but more like inertia.</p>

<p>In my junior year, I discovered that some required courses in my major’s curriculum could actually be replaced by graduate-level alternatives. This option was overheard from more senior students but not documented in the undergraduate curriculum. After conversations with the academic advisor (who has always been a great person!) and course instructors, I enrolled in the graduate version of several courses. 
That was the first time I chose not to follow the “suggested curriculum”, something I had strictly adhered to throughout my education in China (partly because I had no other choices).
This experience made me realize that many rules in schools look strict on paper, but in practice, they can be negotiated, sometimes simply because someone is asking.</p>

<p>Graduate school further reinforced this shift in mindset. 
During my first year, I realized that substantial portions of two core courses had already been covered during college. Simply following the curriculum and retaking the courses seemed meaningless. 
At the same time, I noticed that another supposedly rigid three-course sequence was not as fixed as it appeared. Although the curriculum stated strict prerequisites, I accidentally discovered that the online enrollment system let me register for the final course while taking the first course simultaneously. After several rounds of negotiation with the department, I successfully waived the two core courses, and completed the first and final courses at the same time. I was told that I was the first master’s student in the department to do so. Experiences like these convinced me that many “rules” in school are less like walls but more like doors - the rules open simply because someone is willing to push a little.</p>

<p>Recently I learned a story about Zhenyu Luo (罗振宇), a well-known media entrepreneur in China. Back in 1994, Luo missed the cutoff score for admission to a graduate program at the Beijing Broadcasting Institute by just two points on the politics exam, a result that would normally have ended the process. Instead of accepting this outcome as a “failure”, Luo chose to act aggressively. After hearing rumors about where the admission committee might be visiting, Luo made his way to Changsha, searching through multiple places before finally meeting a committee member in person. Although Luo was not admitted on the spot, his sincerity and determination left a strong impression. When an additional student slot later became available, the committee member recalled Luo and admitted him into the program.</p>

<p>Now I bear a mindset that rules are made by humans; humans make mistakes; rules can be mistakes. If we want something beyond what the rules allow, simply ask, negotiate, and push, thoughtfully and respectfully. The best outcome is success, and the worst is rejection. Regret only comes from never having tried.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="grad-school" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I grew up as a very “乖” kid in China, a Chinese word that has no exact English equivalent but loosely means being well-behaved and obedient, and meeting the expectations that parents and teachers set for good kids and students. I followed rules carefully, behaved the way teachers expected, and internalized the idea that being a good student meant doing things the “right” way. Questioning authority rarely crossed my mind. Rules felt absolute, and obeying them felt like safety and virtue.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Graduate School Taught Me</title><link href="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/graduate_school_start/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Graduate School Taught Me" /><published>2026-01-10T16:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-10T16:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/graduate_school_start</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://limengbinggz.github.io/blog/2026/graduate_school_start/"><![CDATA[<p>Graduate school is often described as a stepping stone toward research careers, accompanied by advanced coursework (at least in the US) and specialized training. All of that is true, yet incomplete. Looking back, what graduate school taught me most was not a specific statistical method, theorem, or software package, but a different way of thinking about learning, work, and myself. This article marks the beginning of a short series in which I reflect on lessons I wish I had understood earlier during my graduate school years. These lessons shaped my career choice immediately after graduate school, and continue to influence how I work today. 
I hope that this series can be helpful to anyone who has ever felt confused, uncertain, or overwhelmed during their own graduate school journey.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="grad-school" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Graduate school is often described as a stepping stone toward research careers, accompanied by advanced coursework (at least in the US) and specialized training. All of that is true, yet incomplete. Looking back, what graduate school taught me most was not a specific statistical method, theorem, or software package, but a different way of thinking about learning, work, and myself. This article marks the beginning of a short series in which I reflect on lessons I wish I had understood earlier during my graduate school years. These lessons shaped my career choice immediately after graduate school, and continue to influence how I work today. I hope that this series can be helpful to anyone who has ever felt confused, uncertain, or overwhelmed during their own graduate school journey.]]></summary></entry></feed>